A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Records of the Special Committee for Program Policy Review in the 1960s FA708
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Records of the Special Committee for Program Policy Review in the 1960s
1952-1963
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA708
3.08 Cubic Feet
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Arrangement
The records ofthe Special Committee are organized in three series:
I. Working Papers of the Special Committee, 1952-1963
II. Proceedings and Report of the Special Committee, 1962
III. Files on the Special Committee Maintained by William McPeak and Terrance Keenan, 1961-1963
Scope and Contents
The records ofthe Special Committee, 1952-1963, the bulk of which were produced from November 1961 to June 1962, were originally part ofJoseph E. Slater's office files. Slater served as the Study Director of the Committee. The Committee is frequently called either "The Slater Committee" after its director, or "The McCloy Review Committee" after John J. McCloy who was the Chairman ofthe Foundation's Board of Trustees when the Committee was established and served as its Chair. Because these documents were created and/or assembled by the Committee during the course of its review of Foundation policies, programs and operations, the decision was made to remove them from Slater's office files and process them as a separate collection.
In July 1995, the register for these records was substantially revised and the records themselves reviewed. The following material concerning the Special Committee was found in the Records Center and added to the records:
• Files originally from the offices ofWilliam McPeak and Terrance Keenan. These now comprise Series III.
• A notebook belonging to Slater with spine label "Special Committee Memoranda" contained some memoranda written by him that were not included in the records. These were interfiled in folder 50 which contains Slate"'s outgoing correspondence.
Biographical / Historical
At its September 1961 meeting, the Board ofTrustees ofthe Foundation "RESOLVED that the Chairman appoint a committee of Trustees and officers to review the programs of the Foundation and report to the Board on program areas which might be newly entered into and programs, if any, which might be discontinued." At the meeting of the Executive Committee of the Board in October, "The Chairman reported on the composition ofthe Committee on Objectives of the Foundation...." Joseph Slater, who had rejoined the Foundation staff at the behest ofJohn J. McCloy to serve as the Study Director of the Committee, acted as rapporteur at the first meeting ofthe Committee which was held on October 26 after the Board's Executive Committee adjourned.
The Committee undertook to review the Foundation's "policies, programs, and operations...and to recommend policies, programs, and operations for the 1960s...." Those appointed to serve on the Special Committee were: John J. McCloy, Chairman of the Board of Trustees (and Chair of the Committee); Donald K. David, Vice Chairman of the Board of Trustees; and Henry T. Heald, President of the Foundation. Other members of the Committee were John Cowles, Julius A. Stratton, Bethuel M. Webster, Milton Katz, Dyke Brown, Clarence H. Faust, F. F. Hill, William McPeak, James M. Nicely, Joseph M. McDaniel, and Joseph E. Slater.
The Committee was ostensibly formed as a ten year review committee, but was also implicitly intended to address proper relationships between Board, President and staff. The Committee assembled staff appraisals of the programs ofthe Foundation in the previous decade and conducted extensive surveys both inside and outside the Foundation to determine courses of action for the future.
The efforts of the Special Committee were broken down into three general phases. Phase one took place from October 1961 to January 1962, during which period the Foundation's past and present programs were appraised. The results are represented in Volume I of 'Supporting Materials,' and are "based primarily upon evaluations by the Foundation staff covering the period 1951-1961."
Also during this phase, "Program Directors and Officers were asked to submit proposals for programs in the 1960s both for their own programs and for the Foundation as a whole. These, together with proposals and suggestions [made] by the Trustees, are in Volume II of 'Supporting Materials.'"
During the second phase (January through April 1962) of the Committee's activities, "wide-ranging interviews with specialists and distinguished leaders were conducted by the Chairman, the Trustee members, and the Study Director... The results are reported in Volume III of 'Supporting Materials.'" Special submissions and papers are summarized in Volume IV.
"On the basis of this supporting material and extensive informal interviews within the Foundation, the Committee held broad discussions during March and April 1962, regarding future programs and policies." The principal problems facing the United States and the world at that time were examined, and the Committee undertook to identify areas in which the Foundation could hope to move with greatest effect during the ensuing decade. Exploration of new areas of interest was not limited to those in the which the Foundation had conducted programs up to that point. "Trustees not members of the Special Committee, and Program Directors, participated actively in these discussions."
During the third and final phase of its project, "the Special Committee considered the institutional, organizational, and financial implications of the new and revised programs and policies it had formulated."
The set of Directives and Terms of Reference resulting from this entire effort were discussed, ammended and then approved by the Board of Trustees at its quarterly meeting in June 1962.
("Directives and Terms of Reference for the 1960s," Introduction, pp. i-ii)
(The Archives has multiple copies of the "Directives..." and the four volumes of supporting materials. In addition, copies ofthe proceedings and the reports in the "Directives..." were placed in the Archives' collection of unpublished staff and consultant reports and cataloged as individual items following the processing of this collection in 1987. See Appendix A for a list of report numbers. In 1995, the "Directives..." and supporting materials were cataloged as report #012673.)
The Foundation also published "The Ford Foundation in the 1960s: Statement of the Board of Trustees on Policies, Programs, and Operations" in July 1962. This volume was intended for distribution outside the Foundation to explain the outcome of the review undertaken by the Special Committee.
For further information on the origins and workings of the Study Committee, see the oral histories of John J. McCloy, Joseph Slater, Willard J. Hertz and W. McNeil Lowry. A review of the Board's consideration of the Directives can be found in the minutes for the June 1962 Board of Trustees meeting.
See also: Ford Foundation Authority File Entries for: • Ford Foundation--Special Committee • Ford Foundation--Policy and Planning
Ford Foundation
- Working Papers of the Special Committee, 1952-1963, I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains supporting material ("source files," charts, reports, summaries of interviews and other material assembled for decision making and use at meetings) and correspondence (letters and memoranda to and from Committee members, agendas, minutes and meeting summaries).
  "Source files" (folders 9-19) contain material kept on potential program areas. They contain interview excerpts, staff submissions prepared as memoranda, miscellaneous notes and letters, and relevant journal and newspaper articles. Included in the first "source file" (box 1, folder 9) is a list of headings used to classify the material in the "source files" which are arranged according to this classification scheme.
  Entries are classified under two broad areas of interest: "Advancement of Peace and International Order and "Invigoration of American Society." Headings under "Advancement of Peace and International Order are coded "A" (for "U.S. Foreign Policy") to "P" (for "Trade with Less-Developed Countries"). Headings under "Invigoration of American Society" are coded "1" (for "U.S. Art and Culture") to "22" (for "Ford Foundation as an Institution").
  Interviews with experts and leaders in a wide variety of fields were conducted by the Chairman, Trustee members, and the Study Director between January and April 1962 (folders 20 to 30). A list categorizing the interviewees and noting the numbers assigned to them is provided in folder 20. The categories are: I. World Affairs; II. Business; III. Labor; IV. Governmental and Congressional; V. Mass Media; VI. Educational and Scientific; and VII. Religious and Cultural.
  The memoranda summarizing these conversations are arranged in numerical order under the name of the Committee member who conducted the interview and are included as supporting material. Notable interviewees include Eleanor Roosevelt (Slater #3), Leonard Bernstein (Slater #55), Adlai Stevenson (Slater #57), Herbert Hoover (McCloy #1), Margaret Mead (Slater #91), and Dean Rusk (Slater #A). Rather than transcribing each interview verbatim, the interviews were summarized in memorandum form by the Committee member responsible.
  In the Correspondence section of Series I (folders 36 to 49), incoming letters deal primarily with suggestions for the focus of the Foundation's activities in the 1960s from leaders and experts in various fields, former and current staff members, and Committee members Milton Katz and Bethuel M. Webster. Originally maintained by the Committee in alphabetical order under the name of the outside correspondent, these files have been reorganized under the names of the Committee members (Henry T. Heald, John J. McCloy, Joseph E. Slater) who received the letters. Alphabetical file order by outside correspondent's name has been maintained within the recipients' files. In addition, each of the above-named Committee members, as well as Milton Katz and Bethuel M. Webster, have outgoing letter files arranged in reverse chronological order.
  Many ofthe letters and memoranda have numbers in the upper righthand comers. These are crossreferences to the interview numbers assigned to each interviewee by members of the Committee. The files include letters from such notable personalities as former U.S. Presidents Harry S. Truman and Herbert Hoover; Congressman Barry Goldwater; and William Benton, publisher and chairman of the Encyclopedia Britannica. Other correspondents include former Foundation staffer Waldemar A. Nielsen and trustee Charles E. Wyzanski. Almost half of the letters to John J. McCloy are in German; most include English translations.
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged in two subseries:
  A. Supporting Materials, 1952-1962
  B. Correspondence, (1956-1957, 1959) 1961-1963
  - Supporting Materials, 1952-1962; A
    This subseries includes:
    • Background Materials on the need for a review of policies in the 1960s • Background Materials for decision making (in report form) • Annual and Cumulative Grant Totals (in chart form) • The Goals Committee analysis for the Special Committee • "Source Files" • Memoranda summarizing internews conducted by Committee members with experts and leaders in a wide variety of fields and activities
    - Notes on the Principles and Policies of the Ford Foundation (Report), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - First Interim Report of Ad Hoc Committee on Special Programs (Report), 1959 June (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Memorandum on Preliminary Phase of Follow-Up Project" - William Pincus, 1960 July (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Background on Need for Review of Policies in the 1960s, 1952 January - 1961 December (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Background Materials for Decision Making (Reports), 1961 November - 1962 February (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Background Materials for Decision Making (Reports), 1962 February - March (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Annual and Cumulative Grant Totals (Charts), 1950 January - 1961 December (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Charts of program categories by year, 1961 December (Box 1, Folder 7a)
    - Goals Committee Analysis for Special Committee by T. Keenan (includes annotations of "Goals for Americans"), 1962 January (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Source File - Advancement of Peace and International Order, A - U.S. Foreign Policy through F - Foreign Understanding of U.S., n.d. - 1962 February (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Source File - Advancement of Peace and International Order, G - General International Understanding, n.d. - 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Source File - Advancement of Peace and International Order, H - U.N. and International Organizationsthrough M - Atlantic Community and Other Regional Communities, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Source File - Advancement of Peace and International Order, N - Economic, Political, Social and Cultural "Development" of Less Developed Countries through O -Trade with Less Developed Countries, n.d. - 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Source File - Invigoration of American Society 1. - U.S. Art and Culture, n.d. - 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Source File - Invigoration of American Society 2. - Education for All Groups, n.d. - 1962 April 12 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Source File - Invigoration of American Society 3. - Race Relations in U.S. through 7. - American Personal and Social Values, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Source File - Invigoration of American Society 8. - Opportunities for Work and Personal Development through 13. - Behavioral Sciences Research, n.d. - 1962 May (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Source File - Invigoration of American Society 14. - Health and Medicine through 17. - Housing and Transportation, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Source File - Invigoration of American Society 18. - Conservation Policy through 19. - Power Systems and Individual Rights, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Source File - Invigoration of American Society 20. - The Public Service through 22. - Ford Foundation as an Institution, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Interviews by Special Committee Members, Illustrative Lists, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Interviews by Special Committee Members, Henry T. Heald #1 - #7, Milton Katz #1 - #3, 1962 January - April (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Interviews by Special Committee Members, John J. McCloy #1- #20, plus one unnumbered, 1962 February - April (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Interviews by Special Committee Members, Joseph E. Slater #A - #9, 1962 January - February (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Interviews by Special Committee Members, Joseph E. Slater #10 - #29, 1962 January (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Interviews by Special Committee Members, Joseph E. Slater #30 - #48 (#41 missing), 1962 January - April (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Interviews by Special Committee Members, Joseph E. Slater #49 - #79 (#57, #59, #62-64, #66-67 missing), 1962 February - March (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Interviews by Special Committee Members, Joseph E. Slater #80 - #92, 1962 March - April (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Joseph E. Slater, Memoranda of Conversations with Trustees, Officers, Program Directors, 1961 December - 1962 March (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Interviews by Special Committee Members, Julius A. Stratton #1, Bethuel M. Webster #1 - #16, 1961 November - 1962 April (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Interviews by Special Committee Members, Summaries of Outside Interviews - Sessions I - XII, 1962 March (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Memoranda for Committee Records (Includes form letters, list of interviewees, summaries of interviews with trustees, officers, program directors), 1961 November - 1962 January (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Recommendations from Outsiders, 1960 May - 1962 April (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Input from the Carnegie Endowment (Joseph E. Johnson, etc.), 1960 April - 1962 January (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Conservation Policy, 1961 - 1962 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Libraries, 1962 March (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, (1956-1957, 1959) 1961-1963; B
    • Incoming Correspondence (letters and memoranda) • Private Correspondence (letters and memoranda) between Joseph E. Slater and John J. McCloy • Letters and Memoranda organizing the Special Committee • Master Copies of administrative memos and letters authorizing Committee meetings • Agendas, Minutes and Summaries of committee meetings • Letters and Clippings reflecting public reaction to the statement issued by the Foundation outlining its policies for the 1960s
    - Letters/Memos Organizing Special Committee, 1961 October - 1962 June (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Administrative Memos and Letters (master copies) Authorizing Committee Meetings, 1961 November - 1962 June (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Agendas, Minutes, Summaries, 1961 November - 1962 June (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Special Committee Meetings, Critical Questions, 1962 March - April (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Henry T. Heald (Incoming), (1956 October - 1957 January) 1962 March - June (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Henry T. Heald (Outgoing), 1959 March - 1962 June (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Milton Katz (Outgoing), 1962 January (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - John J. McCloy Materials, Staff Briefing, 1962 June (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - John J. McCloy (Incoming A-H), 1962 January - July (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - John J. McCloy (Incoming K-Z), 1961 November - 1962 July (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - John J. McCloy (Outgoing), 1962 January - July (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Confidential Communications, Slater/McCloy, 1961 December - 1962 July (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Joseph E. Slater (Incoming A-M), 1961 October - 1962 May (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Joseph E. Slater (Incoming N-W), 1961 November - 1962 November (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Joseph E. Slater (Outgoing), 1962 January - June (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Bethuel M. Webster (Outgoing), 1962 January (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Public Reaction to Statement Issued by FF on its Policies for the 1960s (letters and media articles), 1962 July - 1963 January (Box 4, Folder 52)
- Proceedings and Report of the Special Committee, 1962; II
  Series II contains a carbon copy of the transcript of the Proceedings, sessions I through XII of the Special Committee meetings of March and April 1962 (boxes 5 and 6, folders 63 and 64). (The Archives has an additional copy ofthe transcript in the Vital Records Room, Level C.) The proceedings recount verbatim the discussions between Committee members during these meetings. Also included in this series is a copy of the "Directives and Terms of Reference for the 1960s," the end product of the Committee's efforts, and a draft of the "Directives..." with handwritten revisions and comments by McCloy and Heald (folder 65) along with the four volumes of supporting material. See Appendix B for a guide to the "Directives..." and the supporting material.
  The Foundation's policies and program interests during the 1950s are summarized in Volume I of the Supporting Materials: Ford Foundation Program Evaluation, 1951-61. Volume II is a collection of Trustee and Staff proposals recommending programming directions to be considered in the 1960s. Interview results that include contributions from outside leaders and experts are reported in Volume III. Volume IV contains special papers written by Foundation staff and the principal working papers prepared by Slater. Folders 67 through 72 contain the four volumes of Supporting Materials.
  The "Directives..." present five broad categories, reflecting the recommendations of staff and Trustees, as the principal areas of Foundation concern: Educational Affairs, Arts and Sciences, Public and Economic Affairs, International Affairs, and Overseas Development.
  - Proceedings, Special Committee on Program Review, Sessions I & II, pp. 1-139, 1962 March (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Proceedings, Special Committee on Program Review, Sessions I & II, pp. 140-274, 1962 March (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Proceedings, Special Committee on Program Review, Sessions III & IV, pp. 1-126, 1962 March (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Proceedings, Special Committee on Program Review, Sessions III & IV, pp. 127-241, 1962 March (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Proceedings, Survey Committee of the Ford Foundation, Sessions V & VI, pp. 1-100, 1962 March (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Proceedings, Survey Committee of the Ford Foundation, Sessions V & VI, pp. 101-205, 1962 March (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Proceedings, Survey Committee of the Ford Foundation, Sessions VII & VIII, pp. 1-93, 1962 March (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Proceedings, Survey Committee of the Ford Foundation, Sessions VII & VIII, pp. 94-185, 1962 March (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Proceedings, Special Committee of the Ford Foundation, Sessions IX & X, pp. 1-127, 1962 April (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Proceedings, Special Committee of the Ford Foundation, Sessions IX & X, pp. 128-254, 1962 April (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Proceedings, Special Committee of the Ford Foundation, Sessions XI & XII, pp. 1-88, 1962 April (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Proceedings, Special Committee of the Ford Foundation, Sessions XI & XII, pp. 89-185, 1962 April (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Directives and Terms of Reference for the 1960s (Draft), Revisions by John J. McCloy and Henry T. Heald, 1962 May (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Directives and Terms of Reference for the 1960s Special Committee, Ford Foundation, 1962 June (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Ford Foundation Program Evaluation, 1951-61, Special Committee, Supporting Materials Vol. I, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Ford Foundation Program Evaluation, 1951-61, Special Committee, Supporting Materials Vol. II, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Ford Foundation Program Evaluation, 1951-61, Special Committee, Supporting Materials Vol. III (through Part III, Section III), 1962 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Ford Foundation Program Evaluation, 1951-61, Special Committee, Supporting Materials Vol. III (Part III, Section IV through end), 1962 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Connversations and correspondence with leaders and experts, Special Committee Supporting Materials Vol. III (Parts IV & V), 1962 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Special Papers and Working Documents, Special Committee, Supporting Materials, Vol. IV, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 72)
- Files on the Special Committee Maintained by William McPeak and Terrance Keenan, 1961-1963; III
  Series III has files concerning the Special Comittee that were maintained by William McPeak, a Foundation vice president and member of the Committee, and Terrance Keenan, a writer in the Office of Reports. Keenan's files include his work on drafts of the Directives and related correspondence.
  - Files, William McPeak, 1961 November - 1963 May (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Files, Terrance Keenan, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 74)
- Appendix A
  Appendix A lists those items copied from the Special Committee records and cataloged as part of the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports.
  - Supporting Materials, Volumes I & II, Program Evaluations, 1951-1961, Program Proposals for the 1960s (Report 11151)